Well,
‮حسنًا
welcome to soteriology.
‮مرحبا بكم في علم لاهوت الخلاص‮.
This course deals with the Holy Spirit
‮تتناول هذه الدورة موضوع الروح القدس
and the doctrine of the Holy Spirit,
‮وعقيدة الروح القدس‮.
how the Holy Spirit works in the soul.
‮كيف يعمل الروح القدس في الروح‮.
Running all the way from His effectual calling,
‮بداية من دعوته الفعالة‮،
and regeneration,
‮والتجديد‮،
all the way to glorification.
‮وصولا إلى التمجيد‮.
So it's a very important subject
‮لذلك فهو موضوع مهم للغاية
and I'm glad you're with me.
‮وأنا مسرورلأنكم معي‮.
We're going to look at it in some detail.
‮سوف ننظر في الأمر بشيء من التفصيل‮.
I think you'll enjoy the class.
‮أعتقد أنك ستستمتع بالفصل‮.
After all,
‮بعد كل شيء‮،
all of our
‮كل منا
Christianity,
‮المسيحية‮،
all of our personal religion
‮كل عقيدتنا الشخصية
is just a sham without the Holy Spirit.
‮مجرد خدعة بدون الروح القدس‮.
So we're very,
‮لذلك فنحن
very grateful for the ministry of the Holy Spirit,
‮ممتنون جدا جدا لخدمة الروح القدس ‮،
I want to begin this
‮أريد أن أبدأ هذه
first lecture with the reading of God's word,
‮المحاضرة الأولى بقراءة كلمة الله ‮،
as we will with each each lecture.
‮كما نفعل مع كل محاضرة‮.
Turn with me,
‮اقرأ معي‮،
please,
‮من فضلك‮،
to Romans 8 and I'll read 13 through 17.
‮في رومية ٨ وسأقرأ من ٣١ إلى ٧١‮.
Romans 8: 13 through 17.
‮رومية ٨: ٣١ حتى ٧١‮.
For,
‮لأَنَّهُ
if you live after the flesh,
‮إِنْ عِشْتُمْ حَسَبَ الْجَسَدِ
you shall die.
‮فَسَتَمُوتُونَ
But if ye
‮وَلكِنْ إِنْ كُنْتُمْ
through the Spirit do mortify,
‮بِالرُّوحِ تُمِيتُونَ
the deeds of the body
‮أَعْمَالَ الْجَسَدِ
ye shall live.
‮فَسَتَحْيَوْنَ
For as many as are led
‮لأَنَّ كُلَّ الَّذِينَ يَنْقَادُونَ
by the Spirit of God,
‮بِرُوحِ اللهِ‮،
they are the sons of God.
‮فَأُولئِكَ هُمْ أَبْنَاءُ اللهِ‮.
For you have not received the Spirit
‮إِذْ لَمْ تَأْخُذُوا
of bondage again to fear,
‮رُوحَ الْعُبُودِيَّةِ أَيْضًا لِلْخَوْفِ‮،
but you have received the Spirit of adoption
‮بَلْ أَخَذْتُمْ رُوحَ التَّبَنِّي
whereby we cry Abba,
‮الَّذِي بِهِ نَصْرُخُ:
Father.
‮«يَا أَبَا الآبُ»‮.
The Spirit itself beareth witness with our spirit
‮اَلرُّوحُ نَفْسُهُ أَيْضًا يَشْهَدُ لأَرْوَاحِنَا
that we are the children of God,
‮ أَنَّنَا أَوْلاَدُ اللهِ‮.
and if children then heirs,
‮فَإِنْ كُنَّا أَوْلاَدًا فَإِنَّنَا وَرَثَةٌ أَيْضًا‮،
heirs of God and joint heirs with Christ.
‮وَرَثَةُ اللهِ وَوَارِثُونَ مَعَ الْمَسِيحِ‮.
If so be
‮إِنْ كُنَّا
that we suffer with him,
‮نَتَأَلَّمُ مَعَهُ
that we may also be glorified together.
‮ لِكَيْ نَتَمَجَّدَ أَيْضًا مَعَهُ‮.
Let's seek God's face in prayer.
‮دعونا نطلب وجه الله في الصلاة‮.
Lord God,
‮ايها الرب سيدنا
we stand on holy ground,
‮نقف محضرك المقدس‮،
as we approach this
‮ونحن نقترب من هذا
immense subject of the third person of the Holy Trinity
‮الموضوع الهائل للاقنوم الثالث من الثالوث الأقدس
and his salvific work in our souls.
‮وعمله الخلاصي في نفوسنا‮.
And we do pray that
‮ونحن نصلي بأنه
by the end of this course,
‮بنهاية هذه الدورة‮،
we will have a much more profound appreciation
‮سنتملك إدراكاً عميقاً
for the saving ministry of the Holy Spirit,
‮للعمل الخلاصي للروح القدس
than we perhaps might have at present
‮مما قد يكون لدينا في الوقت الحاضر
Help us to grow,
‮نصلي أن تساعدنا أن ننمو
not only in the grace and knowledge of Jesus,
‮ليس فقط  في معرفة و نعمة يسوع
whom the Spirit focuses upon,
‮والذي يركز عليه الروح‮،
but also that we would grow
‮ولكن أيضًا أن ننمو
in the grace and knowledge of the Holy Spirit,
‮في نعمة الروح القدس ومعرفته‮،
becoming more aware of His work,
‮وأن نصبح أكثر ادراكًا بعمله‮،
His saving work,
‮عمله الخلاصي‮،
and appreciating more profoundly
‮وأن ندرك بعمق
the vastness of His ministry
‮اتساع عمله
as he works in sinners and rebels,
‮إذ يعمل في الخطاة و المتمردين
such as we all are by nature.
‮مثلنا جميعًا بطبيعتنا‮.
So Lord bless this class.
‮لذلك فلتبارك يا رب هذا الفصل‮.
Help me in teaching.
‮ساعدني في التدريس‮.
Help the students in listening,
‮وساعد الطلبة في الاستماع‮،
learning,
‮والتعلم‮،
and grant that each lecture
‮وجعل كل محاضرة
may serve to thy glory,
‮لخدمة مجدك‮،
to our spiritual growth,
‮ولنمونا الروحي‮،
and to the well-being
‮وخيرنا
of our entire being as we journey
‮إذا نسير في رحلتنا
to the never-ending eternity.
‮إلى الأبدية التي لا بلا نهاية‮.
Be with us now we pray.
‮كن معنا الآن!
In Jesus name.
‮في اسم يسوع
Amen.
‮آمين‮.
Well,
‮حسنًا
thank you for joining us for this class
‮شكرا لانضمامكم لنا في هذا الفصل
and I want to
‮وانا اريد ان
begin with the first lecture,
‮ابدأ بالمحاضرة الأولى‮،
which is titled: The Study
‮والتي بعنوان: دراسة
of the Holy Spirit.
‮الروح القدس‮.
The Study of the Holy Spirit.
‮دراسة الروح القدس‮.
God's Holy spirit was with God's people from the beginning.
‮كان روح الله القدوس مع شعب الله منذ البداية‮.
Already in Genesis 1,
‮فها هو منذ تكوين ١‮،
verse 2
‮الآية ٢
leading them ultimately to their rest
‮يقودهم في النهاية إلى راحتهم
in Jesus Christ (Isaiah 63 14)
‮في يسوع المسيح ‮(إشعياء ٣٦: ٤١)
To know the Spirit
‮لنتعرف على الروح
therefore is to stand in continuity
‮يجب ان نستمر في تتبع
with the Saints of all ages.
‮خطوات القديسين عبر العصور
God has promised,
‮لقد وعد الله‮،
his Spirit already to Israel,
‮روحه لإسرائيل‮،
His chosen people.
‮شعبه المختار‮.
We know that in the Old Testament,
‮ونعلم أنه في العهد القديم‮،
various individuals experience a comfort of that Spirit.
‮اختبلا العديد من الاشخاص نعمة الروح القدس
Think of David,
‮فكر في داود‮،
for example (Psalm 51)
‮وعلى سبيل المثال ‮(مزمور ١٥)
But God promised
‮لكن الله قد وعد
a far richer and broader work of the Spirit
‮بعمل أغنى وأوسع للروح
than we might possibly imagine.
‮مما قد نتصوره‮.
Isaiah foretold of a righteous king
‮انبأ اشعياء بملك بار
whose administration would be like,
‮حكمه سيكون مثل‮،
rivers of waters in a dry place
‮أنهار المياه في مكان يابس
and the transformation of the barren wilderness
‮وتتحول البرية القاحلة
into a world filled with the fruit of righteousness (Isaiah 32).
‮إلى عالم مليء بثمار البر ‮(إشعياء ٢٣)‮.
When the Spirit,
‮الى ان الروح‮،
When the Spirit
‮الى ان الروح
is poured out upon us from on high.
‮يًسكب علينا من العلاء‮.
And then he goes on to say in Isaiah 44,
‮ثم يذهب ليقول في إشعياء ٤٤ ‮،
that the Spirit would be poured out on Israel,
‮ان الروح سينسكب على اسرائيل‮،
like a river
‮مثل النهر
of water on dry ground,
‮مثل مجاري المياه على الأرض الجافة‮،
irrigating faithless souls to produce a people
‮تروي النفوس المتمردة ليصير
who say I am the Lord's.
‮شعبا يقول اني للرب‮.
And so the Spirit
‮وكذلك الروح
is the answer of God's covenantal faithfulness
‮هو جواب أمانة الله في العهد
to the chronic problem
‮للمشكلة المزمنة
of Israel's covenant breaking.
‮من كسر عهد إسرائيل‮.
You find that also in
‮ستجد ذلك أيضًا في
the Book of Joel
‮سفر يوئيل
that the Lord would pour out his Spirit upon all his people
‮أن الرب سيسكب  روحه على كل شعبه
that whosoever would call on the name
‮وكل من يدعو باسم
of the Lord would be saved
‮الرب يخلص
(Joel 2:28 to 32).
‮‮(يوئيل ٢:٨٢ إلى ٢٣)‮.
So to study the work of the Holy Spirit
‮لذا فأن دراسة عمل الروح القدس
is to study heavenly work,
‮هي دراسة العمل السماوي‮،
saving work.
‮العمل الخلاصي
And work that abides forever.
‮والعمل الذي يثبت إلى الأبد‮.
Now,
‮والان‮،
of course,
‮بالطبع‮،
in the New Testament age you know,
‮في زمن العهد الجديد كما تعلم‮،
that when Jesus rose from the dead
‮أنه عندما قام يسوع من بين الأموات
and ascended into heaven,
‮وصعد إلى السماء
He poured out His Spirit
‮سكب روحه
in much larger measures than
‮بمقاييس أكبر بكثير مما
had previously been known
‮كان معروفا من قبل
(Acts 2 17,
‮‮(أعمال ٢: ٧١‮،
through 21 and 33 and 34)
‮الى ١٢ و ٣٣ و ٤٣)
And Peter after his sermon is interrupted by
‮فبطرس بعد ان قاطع عظته
thousands of people who are under great conviction of sin.
‮الآلاف من الناس الذين شعروا بتبكيت عظيم بسبب الخطية‮.
Under it
‮الذين هم تحت وطأتها
and they cried out men and Brethren.
‮وصرخوا ايها الرجال الاخوة‮،
What shall we do?
‮ماذا ينبغي ان نفعل؟
Peter said to them,
‮قال لهم بطرس:
repent and be baptized everyone of you
‮تُوبُوا وَلْيَعْتَمِدْ كُلُّ وَاحِدٍ مِنْكُمْ
in the name of Jesus Christ.
‮عَلَى اسْمِ يَسُوعَ الْمَسِيحِ
And you shall receive the gift of the Holy Ghost.
‮فَتَقْبَلُوا عَطِيَّةَ الرُّوحِ الْقُدُسِ
For the promise is unto you
‮لأَنَّ الْمَوْعِدَ هُوَ لَكُمْ
and to your children
‮وَلأَوْلاَدِكُمْ
and to all that are afar off.
‮وَلِكُلِّ الَّذِينَ عَلَى بُعْدٍ
Even as many as the Lord,
‮كُلِّ مَنْ يَدْعُوهُ
Our God shall call (Acts 2: 38 and 39).
‮الرَّبُّ إِلهُنَا ‮(أعمال الرسل ٢: ٨٣ و ٩٣)‮.
And so the rest
‮وهكذا بقية
of the New Testament writings,
‮اسفار العهد الجديد‮،
particularly Paul's Epistles,
‮وخاصة رسائل بولس‮،
are just filled with the Holy Spirit.
‮التي هي مملوءة بالروح القدس
He speaks often
‮وهو غالباً ما يتكلم
about being born
‮عن ولادتهم
of the Spirit such as Galatians,
‮من الروح كما في غلاطية
4: 29.
‮٤:٩٢‮.
And he's talking constantly
‮وهو يتحدث باستمرار
about different aspects
‮حول الجوانب المختلفة
of the Spirit's saving work.
‮لعمل الروح الخلاصي
Like we just read a few
‮كما قرأنا في
of them to you from from Romans 8.
‮رومية ٨‮.
So if we treasure Christ as our only mediator,
‮لذلك إذا كنا نعتز بالمسيح باعتباره الوسيط الوحيد لدينا‮،
we will also treasure the Holy Spirit
‮سوف نعتز أيضًا بالروح القدس
as Christ's great gift,
‮كعطية المسيح العظيمة‮،
which is inseparable from Him,
‮والتي لا ينفصل عنها‮،
to sinners (John 4
‮للخطاة ‮(يوحنا ٤
and again John 7).
‮ومرة أخرى يوحنا ٧)‮.
Jonathan Edwards put it this way.
‮ولقد تحدث جوناثان إدواردز الأمركما يلي:
"The sum of the blessings Christ sought
‮"مجموع البركات التي سعى اليها المسيح
by what he did and suffered
‮من خلال ما فعله وعانى منه
in the work of redemption,
‮في عمل الفداء‮،
was the Holy Spirit,
‮كان هو الروح القدس‮،
the Holy Spirit in His indwelling,
‮الروح القدس في حلوله‮،
His influences and fruits
‮تأثيراته وثماره
is the sum of all grace,
‮هو حصيلة كل النعمة‮،
holiness,
‮والقداسة‮،
comfort and joy,
‮والراحة والفرح‮،
or in one word
‮أو في كلمة واحدة
of all the spiritual good Christ purchased
‮كل خير روحي اقتناه المسيح
for men in this world.
‮للبشر في هذا العالم‮.
And is also the sum of all perfection,
‮وهو أيضًا حصيلة كل الكمالات‮،
glory,
‮والمجد‮،
and eternal joy,
‮والفرح الأبدي‮،
that he purchased
‮الذي اشتراه
for them in another world."
‮لهم في الحياة الابدية "‮.
That's an amazing quote by Edwards.
‮هذا اقتباس رائع من إدواردز‮.
And it certainly shows us
‮وهذا يظهر لنا بالتأكيد
that many today are minimizing
‮أن الكثيرين حالياً يقللون من شأن
the role of the ministry
‮شأن ودور خدمة
of the Holy Spirit as
‮الروح القدس
integral with the entire
‮المتكامل مع الكل
sum of blessings
‮وحصيلة النعم
that God's people receive in salvation.
‮التي ينالها شعب الله في الخلاص‮.
John Brown of Headington
‮جون براون من هيدينغتون
put it this way,
‮طرحها كما يلي:
"Did Christ purchase the Holy Spirit?
‮"هل اقتنى المسيح الروح القدس؟
Christ purchased the Spirit's gifts,
‮هل اشترى المسيح مواهب الروح‮،
and influences in applying redemption,
‮وتأثيراته في تطبيق الفداء‮،
but not his being,
‮ولكن ليس كيانه‮،
which is independent."
‮الذي هو مستقل "‮.
So the work of the Spirit
‮اذا عمل الروح
in many ways
‮بطرق عديدة
is the fruit
‮هو ثمار
of Christ's death and resurrection.
‮موت المسيح وقيامته‮.
Now,
‮والآن‮،
salvation in Christ
‮اصبح الخلاص في المسيح
is appreciated and enjoyed therefore
‮هو موضع تقدير وتلذذ
only by knowing the Holy Spirit
‮فقط من خلال الروح القدس
and his saving work.
‮وعمله الخلاصي‮.
And this is one of the
‮وهذه واحدة من
greatest doctrines of the Reformation,
‮أعظم عقائد الإصلاح‮،
developed so thoroughly and then even
‮التي تم تطويرها بدقة حتى
augmented by the Puritans.
‮عززها البيوريتانيين‮.
What a treasure Reformed theology brings us
‮يا له من كنز يجلبه لنا علم اللاهوت المصلح
about the saving ministry of the Holy Spirit.
‮حول الخدمة الخلاصية للروح القدس‮.
In fact,
‮في الواقع‮،
BB Warfield called John Calvin
‮بي بي وارفيلد دعى جون كالفن
The Theologian of the Holy Spirit.
‮لاهوتي الروح القدس‮.
And Warfield went on to claim
‮واستطرد وارفيلد قائلا
the developed doctrine
‮ان تطور مفهوم
of the work of the Holy Spirit
‮عمل الروح القدس
is an exclusively Reformation doctrine,
‮هوعقيدة الإصلاح حصريًا‮،
and more particularly a Reformed doctrine,
‮وعلى وجه الخصوص العقيدة المصلحة‮،
and still more particularly a Puritan doctrine.
‮ولا يزال على وجه الخصوص عقيدة بيوريتانية‮.
And so,
‮وهكذا‮،
study of the Spirit
‮دراسة الروح
through Reformed experiential soteriology,
‮من خلال علم الخلاص التجريبي المُصلح ‮،
- that is,
‮- هذا هو‮،
salvation that we experience
‮الخلاص الذي نختبره
by the work
‮من خلال عمل
of the Spirit in the soul -
‮الروح في النفس-
opens up a vast wealth of wisdom
‮يفتح كنزهائل من الحكمة
and joy to the believer.
‮والفرح للمؤمن‮.